Current Disputes in the Theory of African Archaeology

A work from my term paper archive.
Directory index

🖨︎ Printable version (PDF) LaTeX source

Submitted
December 14, 2018
Author
Daniel G. Leonard
Course
MSID 4003 Community Engagement in the Global South
Institution
University of Minnesota Twin-Cities
Instructor
Dr. Mwanzia D. Kyule

Abstract

Africa has the oldest evidence of human habitation on the planet. As such, most of its history is open to interpretation by paleoanthropologists. Today, intense disputes occur over the path of human evolution as well as the theory of the field itself. These disputes are discussed.

Introduction

Housing the geographic origin of humans and their primate relatives, Africa has the oldest archaeological record of anywhere on Earth (Holl 2010). Archaeological discoveries taken as markers of human society, such as tool manufacturing, symbolism, and agriculture, find their earliest occurrences in Africa. The Rift Valley of East Africa alone is home to nearly all stone tools claimed to be the oldest (Torre 2011). The draw of archaeologists and their students to Africa can be attributed to this uniquely ancient, uninterrupted history of human evolution and society. As such, the practice and theoretical underpinnings of African archaeology have existed in a state of intense debate and change, evolving at a faster pace than its subjects. Little is settled fact in this discipline, from the earliest history to the present day.

Western and Colonial Influence on the Development of African Archaeology

African archaeology is inexorably marked by its relationship to the Western colonial project and global capitalism. As a scientific discipline, archaeology arose from the era of Enlightenment in Western Europe, and developed from the era’s understanding of history. As such, the underlying paradigms often conflict with the needs and historical conception of African societies (Schmidt 1995; Shepherd 2002).

The Colonial Era

Colonialism in Africa served to provide labor and resources to Western capital, and anthropologists on the continent were primarily Western Enlightenment-era thinkers, employed by the colonial administration or European universities. Archaeology served as a tool of the colonial government, whose findings coincidentally served as justification for the right of Europeans to rule over the continent. European archaeology denied the extant African population the right to claim as their heritage any complex social structures discovered in the archaeological record, and used this denial to explain the “backwardness” of Africans and thus the necessity for European conquest (Koff 1997).

An exemplary example of this is that of Great Zimbabwe, a series of stone ruins in southern Africa. The South Africa Company in its initial commissions for study of the site specified the necessity to find evidence for their European origin, and denied from the outset any claims Black Africans’ claims to the heritage. Early archaeologists and colonial architects thus attributed the site to ancient peoples of the Levant rather than the resident African population, and would defend this conclusion virulently. The company’s results were used to justify their own conquest of southern Africa as a return to their homeland. Professional archaeologists, many of whom took opposing viewpoints on the origin of Great Zimbabwe and on other southern African historical dilemmas, found themselves censored by the colonial administration (Koff 1997; Shepherd 2002).

Archaeology in Independence Movements

During and after independence, the practice of African archaeology reflected a new social and political system. Some African nationalist movements sought to reclaim the prehistory of the continent, taking their ancestral history back from the colonial empires. Today’s majority-ruled Republic of Zimbabwe, for instance, gets its name from the archaeological site which had been the subject of colonial falsification. Likewise, Nigeria, Senegal, Ghana, and Zambia all introduced archaeology to the students of their new national universities, allowing Africans to voice their own histories (Koff 1997).

Other nationalist movements were slow to adopt archaeology as a discipline. In Kenya, archaeology outside that of early human evolution has failed to see the light of day, with most archaeologists being Europeans following in the footsteps of the Leakeys (Koff 1997). Schmidt (1995) has argued that this white-dominated focus on paleoanthropology is an ideological choice by the government: the Kenyan ruling elite is threatened by the land claims of the country’s ethnic groups, many of whom had their traditional land holdings replaced with prejudice against each other by the British “divide & conquer” strategy.

Archaeology, if allowed to flourish at a regional level, can easily be identified with an attempt to valorize the history … of one ethnic group at the perceived expense of others. The state’s deep investment in the white intellectuals’ pursuit of ancient human ancestors has been an ideal way to neutralize regional histories … it focuses on a ‘population’ devoid of ethnicity – indeed, devoid of humanness.

– Schmidt (1995, 128–29)

Just as archaeology served the ideological goals of the colonial empire, post-independence scholarship continues to reflect the dilemmas within African political spheres.

Rise of Homo sapiens

Despite the African continent’s undisputed status as the geographic origin of early primates and hominins, debate still arises over the particulars of how members of the genus Homo interacted with one another and spread throughout the world. Paleoanthropologists are certain that H. habilis lived exclusively in Africa, followed by populations of H. erectus, H. heidelbergensis, and presently H. sapiens, all of whom appear to have had significant presence on the Eurasian continent (Wenke and Olszewski 2007). How these populations interacted and evolved is uncertain.

Early Hominin Expansion

Homo erectus was most likely the first hominin to venture off the African continent, with a range of sites from southeast Asia to the Iberian Peninsula. Compared to H. sapiens, H. erectus had more protruding jaws, smaller cranial capacity, and larger brow ridges (see Wenke and Olszewski 2007, fig. 4.2). H. erectus likely lived in caves and used fire, suggesting adaptability to the cold climates outside Africa. Evidence strongly suggests H. erectus manufactured tools, with H. erectus sites containing tools dating to .6 Ma in Europe and over 1 Ma in Africa. Various improvements in toolmaking may have allowed H. erectus to adapt to the wide variety of climates and ecosystems encountered throughout the species’ historical range. Specifically, the Acheulian hand-axe shows a creativity in its craftsmanship, requiring forethought and an implicit understanding of stone flaking behavior. Its widespread range suggests a versatility in use unmatched in preceding hominin technology (Wenke and Olszewski 2007).

H. neanderthalensis (sometimes H. sapiens neanderthalensis) emerged around .5 Ma in Europe and Central Asia, with a physical structure vastly similar to that of anatomically-modern humans. H. neanderthalensis showed some adaptations compared to H. erectus to the cold weather of their native Europe, with more massive and muscular bodies. The species also appears to have practiced burials and manufactured specialized stone tools, a marked similarity to H. sapiens in comparison to H. erectus.

The lack of a direct line of hominin remains showing flows of single populations, as well as the phenotypical similarities and gradients within the remains of early hominins, make it difficult to pinpoint the origin of anatomically modern humans. Theories have thus arisen to explain the genetic and phenotypical differences current H. sapiens shows across geographic regions.

Out-of-Africa II

The replacement model, better known as the “out-of-Africa II” hypothesis, proposes that H. sapiens originated exclusively in Africa and spread to Eurasia recently. This wave of emigration drove the already-present Eurasian Homo populations, who had migrated nearly a million years beforehand in “out-of-Africa I,” to extinction, “replacing” them. In the 1980s, paleoanthropologists accepted the idea of H. sapiens appearing around .2 Ma and rapidly spreading outside Africa, completely replacing populations of hominins without any population mixture (Kendrick 2014).

The oldest H. sapiens fossils have all been found in Africa, with Richard Leakey’s Omo River Valley fossils dated to 195 ka. Further, transitional fossils have only been found on the African continent, with absences of any transitional remains in Eurasia or Australasia. Morphologically, African fossils show the greatest internal diversity as well as the greatest difference from all non-African populations. Even without genetic testing, replacement theory was accepted as the story of human evolution by the 1980s (Kendrick 2014).

Recent genetic evidence provides further support for this second migration of humans. Because mitochondria have their own genetic sequence and are passed down exclusively maternally, geneticists have been able to hunt for a maternal ancestor of all living humans. Cann, Stoneking, and Wilson (1987) studied the mitochondrial DNA sequences of 147 people and, extrapolating from the known rate of mutation of DNA, concluded that all living populations today derive from one ancestor who lived approximately .2 Ma, likely in Africa.

Multiregional Hypothesis

The multiregional or regional-continuity hypothesis proposes that modern H. sapiens are the result of contact and interbreeding between disparate human populations across Eurasia. What is now one human species is seen as the result of convergent evolution from different members of the genus Homo who interacted and – at least partially – united globally.

Multiregionalists point to the presence of unique genes in European H. sapiens populations, attributed to interbreeding with H. neanderthalensis. Thus, it is likely that what came to be H. sapiens is the result of mergers between formerly distinct hominin populations. Conversely, they criticize the use of mitochondrial DNA by replacement theorists, citing it as based on unfounded assumptions (Kendrick 2014).

Morphologically, the extant peoples of Eurasia and Africa are quite distinct. Followers of multiregional theory use this discrepancy as evidence for distinct evolutionary paths, which gained distinct genetic traits from separate species of Homo (Kendrick 2014).

Prehistoric African Art

Some of the earliest evidence for anatomically modern humans is the art they left behind. Cave paintings, pottery, and beadwork are all major classes of artifacts in African archaeology. Especially with rock art, the existence of these have long enthralled European archaeologists; however, the European conception of art brings with it cultural baggage (Arnaut 1991). Postmodern criticism of these research topics have questioned the veracity of whether we can “know” anything about what the creators of such creations were thinking at the time. It is tempting to consider these from the standpoint of the Western conception of art, yet it is impossible to know what a hominin to which we have no social connection could have ever thought during its lifetime.

References

Arnaut, Karel. 1991. “Art and the African World: A Historical Analysis of Their Interconnection.” JASO 22 (2): 151–65.

Cann, Rebecca L., Mark Stoneking, and Allan C. Wilson. 1987. “Mitochondrial DNA and Human Evolution.” Nature, 31–36. doi:10.1038/325031a0.

Holl, Augustin F. C. 2010. “The Archaeology of Africa.” In Archaeology, edited by Donald L. Hardesty, II:21–66. United Kingdom: Eolss Publishers Co. Ltd.

Kendrick, James. 2014. “Rethinking Modern Human Origins: Getting Out of Out of Africa.” Assemblage 13: 1–13.

Koff, Clea. 1997. “On Two Eras of African Archaeology: Colonial and National.” Nebraska Anthropologist 14: 47–57.

Schmidt, Peter Ridgway. 1995. “Using Archaeology to Remake History in Africa.” In Making Alternative Histories: The Practice of Archaeology and History in Non-Western Settings, edited by Thomas Carl Patterson and Peter Ridgway Schmidt, 119–47. School of American Research Press.

Shepherd, Nick. 2002. “The Politics of Archaeology in Africa.” Annual Review of Anthropology 31: 189–209. doi:10.1146/annurev.anthro.31.040402.085424.

Torre, Ignacio de la. 2011. “The Origins of Stone Tool Technology in Africa: A Historical Perspective.” Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B 366 (1567): 1028–37. doi:10.1098/rstb.2010.0350.

Wenke, Robert F., and Deborah J. Olszewski. 2007. Patterns in Prehistory: Humankind’s First Three Million Years. 5th ed. Oxford: Oxford University Press.

Challenges Faced in the Termination of Persons with Disabilities from a Segregated Workshop in Mombasa, Kenya

A work from my term paper archive.
Directory index

🖨︎ Printable version (PDF) LATEX source

Submitted
December 14, 2018
Author
Daniel G. Leonard
Course
MSID 4003 Community Engagement in the Global South
Institution
University of Minnesota Twin-Cities
Instructor

Dr. Mohamud A. Jama
Dr. Mohamed Karama

Abstract

The Association for the Physically Disabled of Kenya (APDK) provides rehabilitation programs for persons with disabilities as well as segregated labor opportunities. In Mombasa, Kenya, ADPK operates Bombolulu Workshops and Cultural Centre as a segregated housing complex, containing work programs in producing fair-trade jewelry and mobility aids. Ability to permanently reside at the facility is tied to continued employment at the organization, which for laborers dismissed in cost-cutting retrenchments in 2011 and 2012 has presented difficulties in living and housing. The objective of this study was to assess the effect of dismissal on quality-of-life in persons with disabilities resident at Bombolulu. The study was conducted via interviews with administration, one focus group discussion amongst terminated employees, and observation of facility operations over the course of six weeks. The sheltered workshop model was found to produce marked gains in quality-of-life, yet these effects are nullified upon employees’ termination. The future of the sheltered workshop model is discussed.

Introduction

Persons with disabilities (PWDs) have unique challenges in the labor market and in their daily lives.

Persons with disabilities in the labor force

The disability status of an individual is a major predictor of one’s labor force participation, for a wide range of disabling symptoms (Stern 1989). This has been exacerbated in the West under contemporary neoliberal policies, which frequently require paid work as a prerequisite to receiving state welfare benefits, rather than welfare being a redistributive public service (Lister 1998; Wilton and Schuer 2006). This shift been undertaken ostensibly to liberate persons with disabilities from the yoke of government dependency, yet it has failed to provide accessible labor opportunities for these people to enter (Wilton and Schuer 2006). As a result, persons with disabilities have experienced increased necessity to compete for employment.

In Kenya, persons with disabilities are widely excluded from the labor market. Of 1,697 persons surveyed in the country, only 16.3% had primarily spent their last week in paid employment (National Coordinating Agency for Population and Development and Kenya National Bureau of Statistics 2008). When including work within family businesses – the informal sector possesses a considerable proportion of Kenya’s laborers (Livingstone 1991) – the total amount of Kenyans with disabilities in consistent employment remains extremely low at 49.6%. 7.2% of Kenyans surveyed reported never having been employed, with most of these respondents being in the 15-24-year-old cohort.

Compounding this phenomenon is a lack of access to education for Kenyans with disabilities. In the same national study, over 70% of respondents had not attended schooling past the primary education level, and 4% report having experienced having been refused entry into a school due to disability.

Segregated Communities

There is a long history of segregated employment opportunities for persons with disabilities. In the United States since 1840, segregated educational and labor opportunities have been available for the disabled in order to shelter them from competition on the labor market, where it was expected that they would surely be overlooked (National Disability Rights Network 2011). Even today, United States federal law provides an exemption to the minimum wage for persons with disabilities in section 14 (c) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938, who are permitted to be paid lower rates than abled workers. The vast majority of certificates authorizing employment of disabled workers at below minimum wage are awarded to rehabilitation centers, where disabled people perform paid labor in a segregated setting (Employment Stadards Administration 1991). The National Disability Rights Network has on this point objected strongly to the continuation of segregated employment in the United States, calling the system a condescending and oppressive “dead end” for workers with disabilities (National Disability Rights Network 2011, 32). However, Cobley (2012) argues that in the developing world, building broad-based support mechanisms is a more pressing goal than true integration.

While many sheltered workshops may encourage long-term or permanent employment, it is inevitable that workers will depart from their positions, as in any formal employment situation. Persons with disabilities, however, exist in a more precarious state than abled workers and can be expected to be affected by loss of employment differently than others. Specifically, the termination of an employee can have a strong influence on a person’s life. This study set out to survey the effects of termination on employees of a facility run by the Association for the Physically Disabled of Kenya (APDK).

Methodology

Study Site

APDK provides rehabilitative and assistance services to persons with physical disabilities throughout Kenya. In the coastal city of Mombasa and the surrounding areas, APDK’s Coast Branch operates three large facilities. Bombolulu Workshops and Cultural Centre employs PWDs in the production of jewelry, textiles, wheelchairs, and toys, as well as in presentations of indigenous Kenyan cultural activities for visitors. Likoni Furniture Workshop is another sheltered workshop invested in the manufacturing of high-end furniture. Port Reitz Rehabilitation Clinic, an independent part of the larger state-owned Port Reitz District Hospital, specializes in long-term inpatient care for children with correctable physical disabilities, including a small classroom to ensure continuous education even when treatment occurs during the school year. At Bombolulu and Likoni Workshops, most employees are provided housing in residential facilities owned by APDK and cordoned off from the rest of the town, paid for out of the garnished wages of residents. Both workshops have also been the subject of former study by Cobley (2012). APDK Coast Branch also operates a microfinance program referred to as Income-Generating Programme (IGP) or Faida (Swahili-language word for “profit”), issuing small loans to PWDs for the operation and maintenance of their own small businesses in the informal sector (for further discussion of the Faida program, see Wameyo 2015; also Cobley 2012).

At Bombolulu Workshops, the subject of this study, commodity production is primarily for export. Global fair-trade jewelry retailers are the organization’s largest clients, with produced items affixed the brand of the client before packaging. Despite frequent high-volume sales, the organization is most reliant on donations from non-governmental organizations to fund its operations, previously reported by Cobley (2012). In 2011 and 2012, the organization terminated over twenty of their permanent staff to cut costs. These former employees were instructed to vacate their APDK-owned residences, yet still reside on-site due to a judicial injunction temporarily preventing their eviction.

Data Collection

The study was performed through four interviews with APDK Coast Branch administrative staff, one focus group discussion, and observation of employees’ and administrators’ activities over the course of six weeks working alongside production staff. Topics discussed with administrators covered compensation of workers, costs of state of APDK finances, and reasons for employees’ departure. The group discussion consisted of twenty-one former employees who had been dismissed in the retrenchments of 2011 and 2012. Following the taxonomy of social-science group discussions outlined by Frey and Fontana (1991) the discussion conducted at Bombolulu was structured as a formal field interview and phenomenological in nature. Questions focused on quality of life before and during residence at Bombolulu, compensation for work, and life prospects post-dismissal. A currently-employed member of the bureaucratic staff served as an interpreter for Swahili and a volunteer from within the group translated to and from Kenyan Sign Language.

Findings

Project Sustainability

Administrators throughout APDK Coast Branch lamented the organization’s reliance on donations, expressing a desire for their projects’ self-sufficiency. At Bombolulu and Likoni, frequent reference was made to a decline in funding, blamed primarily on a change in donors’ opinions on the efficacy and morality of sheltered workshops. Reference was frequently made to the U.N. Declaration on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, whose ratification by the Kenyan government was paradoxically followed by a decline in donations to APDK. Staff explained this discrepancy as the result of foreign donors’ belief in the passage of disability-focused law as inherently implying its effective enforcement.

Today, many of the residential blocks at Bombolulu are commercially rented to abled persons in order to generate revenue, a break from APDK’s initial goals of providing shelter for the needy.

Quality of Life in Kenya

Workers described their lives before APDK as a spiral of poverty. They had felt ignored by society, with a lack of medical attention or accessible education. Only a handful graduated secondary school, although a few did graduate from post-secondary education. Even for college graduates, it was difficult or impossible to find stable employment. Those with degrees were no more likely to report having had independent employment than those without a primary school education, and those who did still described heavy dependence on family for care and shelter. Jobs attained were almost exclusively in tailoring or as house help, with little variation. Compounding these effects were the impacts of single motherhood, a frequently cited problem for the women who made up a majority of the group discussion’s participants, detailing that their male partners had fled upon learning of their pregnancy.

Employment

Usually by word-of-mouth, discussion participants had in young adulthood learned of APDK’s sheltered workshop programs and traveled to Mombasa to seek employment. The promise of independence was the greatest draw for them, as dependence on family for basic necessities well into adulthood felt humiliating. At APDK, workers felt that they could be the arbiter of their own destinies. As one worker described life became easy for the first time. For those with children to care for, a home of one’s own and a reliable paycheck was invaluable. Daycare services are available at Bombolulu even for non-affiliated families outside APDK, and during the school break – when this study took place – it was common to observe children playing throughout the day on the large sports field and playground.

Not all aspects of tenure at Bombolulu were so described as a blessing. The former workers described low salaries and a high cost of living while at the facility. Most found it possible to sustain themselves at the most basic level, yet most agreed with one worker who stated, I couldn’t save even a shilling. Administrators reported the average salary to be 17,600 KES (approx. $176 USD) per month, after garnishment for residential utility costs. However, workers detailed that payment was based on individual production, not on labor-hours worked. Some reported having worked dawn-to-dusk to meet their production quotas, with no overtime. Concurrently, there was a shared resentment amongst workers regarding the administration – primarily seen as able-bodied – raising their own salaries while the aging workforce struggled to make ends meet. Despite having full-time employment, the workers reported having to survive on loans from an informal credit union formed amongst themselves. Several workers described having gone stretches of up to two days without food, waiting for the next paycheck.

Effect of Termination

When Bombolulu administration declared the cost-cutting retrenchments in 2011 and 2012 of those who comprised the focus group discussion, advance notice was given one month beforehand. The workers, however, thought one month’s warning was inadequate. Having expected to work for APDK until retirement age, dismissal left the laborers in a position of uncertainty whether they would be able to find employment outside. Compounding this was the mandate to vacate their employer-supplied housing, a labor relation uncommon in factory work. Despite receiving a court injunction temporarily permitting continued residence, many live in fear of the day they are permanently evicted. No members of the discussion said they knew of a place to move to should they have to leave Bombolulu.

APDK’s mission statement is to enable persons with different abilities to overcome their physical limitations by empowering them economically and socially so that they become fully-integrated members of their communities, inscribed on the external wall of a housing block clearly visible upon entry into Bombolulu. During the focus group discussion, a collective murmur discord echoed in response to recital of this statement. Regarding economic empowerment, the workers felt that their socioeconomic position had not improved during the course of their tenures, going so far as to declare that their lives are more difficult now than before entering the employ of APDK. Many had worked since young adulthood, and now lacked the vitality they had possessed at the time of their application to work at Bombolulu. Families who had formerly provided support were cited as no longer being able to, having aged in the decades their children had worked for APDK. Furthermore, many had chosen to raise families at the workshop, and without income or savings it has become difficult to provide for them. As one worker put it, I’ve gone from the support of a family to supporting a family.

These resentments have led to concern in the eyes of the terminated workers over whether APDK administration truly cares for PWDs’ quality of life. As one worker stated and several concurred, this place was founded by persons with disabilities, it belongs to us.

Discussion

Despite grandiose goals, APDK’s use of the sheltered workshop model has presented issues both in its sustainability and in its ability to care for PWDs. In concurrence with what Cobley (2012) and National Disability Rights Network (2011) have argued, the segregated system fails PWDs in many ways and serves to maintain a two-tier employment system. Workers feel cut-off and are unable to reach the promised self-sufficiency. It is advised that disability-rights organizations continue to make inclusive approaches, as discussed by Cobley (2012).

Limitations

Due to restrictions on independent undergraduate research, it was not possible to conduct one-on-one interviews with non-administrative employees of APDK. No focus group discussion was conducted amongst those currently in the employ of the workshops, as was planned, nor amongst those who had retired and vacated their residences of their own volition, most of whom no longer lived near Mombasa. The single focus group discussion in this study took three weeks to organize, and as it was held in the final week of the study no follow-up inquiries could be investigated.

References

Cobley, David S. 2012. “Towards Economic Empowerment: Segregation Versus Inclusion in the Kenyan Context.” Disability & Society 27 (3): 371–84. doi:10.1080/09687599.2012.654988.

Employment Stadards Administration. 1991. “Minimum Wage and Maximum Hours Standards Under the Fair Labor Standards Act.” Washington, D.C.: Department of Labor; United States Department of Labor; Government Printing Office.

Frey, James H., and Andrea Fontana. 1991. “The Group Interview in Social Research.” The Social Science Journal 28 (2): 175–87. doi:10.1016/0362-3319(91)90003-M.

Lister, Ruth. 1998. “From Equality to Social Inclusion: New Labour and the Welfare State.” Critical Social Policy 18 (55): 215–25. doi:10.1177/026101839801805505.

Livingstone, Ian. 1991. “A Reassessment of Kenya’s Rural and Urban Informal Sector.” World Development 19 (6): 651–70. doi:10.1016/0305-750X(91)90200-2.

National Coordinating Agency for Population and Development, and Kenya National Bureau of Statistics. 2008. “Kenya National Survey for Persons with Disabilities.” Nairobi.

National Disability Rights Network. 2011. “Segregated & Exploited: The Failure of the Disability Service System to Provide Quality Work.” Washington, D.C.

Stern, Steven. 1989. “Measuring the Effect of Disability on Labor Force Participation.” The Journal of Human Resources 24 (3): 361–95. doi:10.2307/145819.

Wameyo, Janet Bwiza. 2015. “Effect of Microfinance Services on the Growth of Persons with Disabilities Self Help Groups in Kenya.” Master’s thesis, College of Humanities; Social Sciences; University of Nairobi. http://hdl.handle.net/11295/94148.

Wilton, Robert, and Stephanie Schuer. 2006. “Towards Socio‐spatial Inclusion? Disabled People, Neoliberalism and the Contemporary Labour Market.” Area 38 (2): 186–95. doi:10.1111/j.1475-4762.2006.00668.x.